Inventory of the Preston Family Papers 1755-1826
Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
{Special Collections, University of Virginia Library}
Preston Family Papers, 1755-1836, 1786-1815.
Special Collections, College of William and Mary
Mss. 39.1 P91
90 items.
This inventory is dated primarily from 1786 to 1815, and concerns three generations of the Preston family of western Virginia. The papers reflect their involvement in the administrative and political life of Virginia and the nation, as well as family concerns on the Virginia frontier.
Preston Family,; William Preston,; Francis Preston,; John Preston,; William C. Preston.
Administrative Information
Restrictions on Access
Collection is open to all researchers.
Acquisition Information
Gift: 90 items, 05/25/1940.
Alternative Form
Several of the items in this collection have been reprinted. These include the letters written between 1786-1813, by John Preston to Francis Preston printed in the William and Mary Quarterly, 2nd Ser., Vol. 1, pp. 42-51 and Vol. 2, pp. 188-193. A list of these items is located below. A typed list is located in the first folder of the collection.
18 May 1786. John Preston to Francis Preston. Series 2, Vol. 1, pp. 42-45.
2 November 1786. John Preston to Francis Preston. Series 2, Vol. 1, pp. 45-47.
26 December 1786. John Preston to Francis Preston. Series 2, Vol. 1, pp. 47-49.
17 February 1787. John Preston to Francis Preston. Series 1, Vol. 27, pp. 203-205.
31 May 1793. John Preston to Francis Preston. Series 2, Vol. 2, pp. 188-189 [dated as 3 May].
25 Nov. 1794. John Preston to Francis Preston. Series 2, Vol. 2, p. 187.
14 May 1799. John Preston to Francis Preston. Series 2, Vol. 1, pp. 49-51.
19 December 1802. John Preston to Francis Preston. Series 2, Vol. 2, pp. 189-192.
3 March 1813. John Preston to Francis Preston. Series 2, Vol. 2, pp. 192-193.
Some letters are also available in typescript.
Biographical Information
William Preston (ca. 1729-1783) held various county offices and militia offices. His sons were John Preston (1764-1827), who was a member of the Virginia General Assembly and treasurer of Virginia, and Francis Preston (1765-1836). Francis Preston was born in Botetourt County, graduated from the College of William and Mary and practiced law in Montgomery and Washington counties. He served in the Virginia House of Delegates and State Senate and served in Congress 1793-1797. His son was William Campbell Preston (1794-1860) who attended Washington College (now Washington and Lee University) and South Carolina College (now University of South Carolina). He also studied law in Scotland and practiced in Virginia and later in South Carolina. He served in the South Carolina House of Representatives and in the United States Senate. William Campbell Preston was president of South Carolina College.
Scope and Content Information
This inventory, chiefly 1786-1815, represents three generations of the Preston family, and likewise can be divided into the following:
Items relating to William Preston (ca. 1729-1783), 1755-1782, primarily photostats of appointments to various county offices (coroner, sheriff and surveyor) and to positions in the Virginia militia; but also including original appointments, 1763 and 1776; a surveyor's entry; 1774; and letters, 1773-1782, to Preston concerning land, the Cherokee Indians and a court martial.
Items, 1785-1819, relating to William's sons, Francis Preston (1765- 1836), lawyer, member of the Virginia Legislature and the U.S. Congress; and his brother John Preston (1764-1827), member of the Virginia Assembly and long-time Treasurer of Virginia, including letters from John Preston to Francis Preston as well as correspondence of the two men with other people. Subjects covered in the letters include politics; the War of 1812; a carriage; the College of William and Mary; duels; the building of a house; and Indians. These papers also contain a certificate, 20 September 1793, of emancipation for a slave signed by Francis Preston; and his appointment of two military aides.
Items relating to the correspondence of William Campbell Preston (1764- 1860), son of Francis Preston, and a member of Congress from South Carolina, including a circular and letter, 1827, concerning protest by citizens of South Carolina of a protective tariff.
Arrangement
Organization
This inventory has been organized into four Series: 1. William Preston Papers; 2. Francis Preston Papers; 3. John Preston Papers; 4. William C. Preston Papers.
Arrangement
Each folder contains the papers of their creators/persons, identified by series title. Items are then arranged chronologically by date.
Additional Descriptive Data
Related Material
Other related material concerning the Preston family can be found in the Robert Morton Hughes Papers at Old Dominion University.
Index Terms
Family Names:
Preston family.
Persons:
Preston, William, ca. 1729-1783.; Preston, John, 1764- 1827.; Preston, Francis, 1765-1836.; Preston, William C. (William Campbell), 1794-1860.
Subjects:
College of William and Mary--History--18th century.; Cherokee Indians--History.; Dueling--Virginia.; Architecture, Domestic--Virginia.; Indians of North America--History--19th century.; Slavery--Virginia--History-- 18th century.; Tariff--United States--History.; Carriage and wagon making.; Virginia--Militia.; United States--Politics and government-- 1789-1815.; United States--History--War of 1812.
Components List
  Series 1: William Preston Papers
- William Preston Papers, 1755-1782, 16 items. (Folder 1)
  - Certificate of appointment of William Preston, 14 Feb[ruar]y 1755., 1 page. Pst Cy of PDS. (Folder 1)
    William Preston was appointed as "Captain of a Company of Rangers in Augusta County," [Virginia]. Signed by Rob[er]t Dinwiddie, Williamsburg, Virginia.
  - Certificate of appointment of William Preston, 11 December 1758., 1 page. Pst Cy of PDS. (Folder 1)
    William Preston was appointed as "Captain of a Company of Rangers." Signed by Fran[cis] Fauquier, Williamsburg, Virginia.
  - Certificate of appointment of William Preston, 14 June 1759., 1 page. Pst Cy of PDS. (Folder 1)
    William Preston was appointed as: "Lieut[enan]t Col[one]l of the Militia for the County of Augusta," [Virginia]. Signed by Fran[cis] Fauquler, Williamsburg, Virginia.
  - Certificate of appointment of William Preston, 18 October 1759., 1 page. Pst Cy of PDS. (Folder 1)
    William Preston was appointed as Escheator for Augusta County, Virginia. Signed by Fran[cis] Fauquier, Williamsburg, Virginia.
  - Certificate of appointment of William Preston, 2 August 1763., 1 page. PDS. (Folder 1)
    William Preston was appointed as "Colonel of the Militia for the County of Augusta," [Va.]. Signed by Fran[cis] Fauquie[r], Williamsburg, Virginia.
  - Certificate of appointment of William Preston, 22 December 1769., 1 page. Pst Cy of PDS. (Folder 1)
    William Preston was appointed as "Colonel of the Militia of the County of Botetourt," [Va.]. Signed by [Norborne Berkeley, Baron de] Botetourt, Williamsburg, Virginia.
  - Certificate of appointment of William Preston, 22 December 1769., 1 page. Pst Cy of DS. (Folder 1)
    William Preston was appointed as "one of our Coroners of our County of Botetourt," Virginia. Signed by [Norborne Berkeley, Baron de] Botetourt, Williamsburg [Virginia].
  - Certificate of appointment of William Preston, 1 December 1772., 1 page. Pst Cy of PDS. (Folder 1)
    William Preston was appointed as "Sheriff of the County of Fincastle [County, later Kentucky, and Montgomery and Washington Counties, Virginia], [Virginia]. Signed by [John Murray, Earl of] Dunmore, Williamsburg, Virginia.
  - Letter from W[illia]m Campbell, Aspen Bottom, [?], to [William] Preston, n.p., 6 Feb. 1773., 1 page. ALS. (Folder 1)
    Letter concerns Capt. Shelby's purchase of the land where Capt. Bledsoe lives.
  - Surveyor's entry of Fincastle [County, later Kentucky and Montgomery and Washington Counties, Virginia], Virginia, 15 August 1774., 1 page. ADS. (Folder 1)
    Item mentions [William] Preston, surveyor of Fincastle. Signed by William Christian.
  - Certificate of appointment of William Preston, 7 October 1775., 1 page. Pst Cy of PDS. (Folder 1)
    William Preston was appointed as "Lieutenant and Commander in chief of the Militia of the County of Fincastle [County, later Kentucky, and Montgomery and Washington Counties, Virginia], Virginia" Signed by the Committee of Safety for the Colony of Virginia.
  - Letter from Anthony Bledsoe, Fort Patrick Henry, [Virginia], to Col[one]l [William Preston], n.p., 8 Dec. 1776., 1 page. ALS. (Folder 1)
    Letter concerns the Cherokee Indians, their need of supplies, and their fear of coming to Williamsburg.
  - Certificate of appointment of William Preston, 21 Dec[embe]r 1776., 1 page. Pst Cy of PDS. (Folder 1)
    William Preston was appointed as "County Lieutenant of Militia in the County of Montgomery," [Virginia]. Signed by P[atrick] Henry, Williamsburg, Virginia.
  - Certificate of appointment of William Preston, 11 March 1780., 1 page. Pst Cy of PDS. (Folder 1)
    William Preston was appointed as "Surveyor for the County of Montgomery," [Virginia]. Signed by Dudley Digges, L[ieutenant] G[overnor], Williamsburg, Virginia.
  - Letter from Charles Morgan, n.p., to William Preston, n.p., 6 May 1782., 2 pages. ALS. (Folder 1)
    Letter concerns a court martial of two men, Marshall Duncan and Timothy Roark, and the circumstances involved in the case; and men trying, to be struck from the muster roll in order to be relieved of their military duties.
  - Post bond for Joseph Achillberger before W[illia]m Preston, Justice of the Peace, Montgomery County, Virginia, 20 June 1782., 1 page. AD. (Folder 1)
  Series 2: Francis Preston Papers
- Francis Preston Papers, 1786-1799., 35 items. (Folder 2-3)
  - Letter from J[ohn] Preston, "Smithfield," [Montgomery County, Virginia], to "brother," Fran[ci]s Preston, n.p., 18 May 1786., 4 pages. ALS. Including typescript of 2 pages. (Folder 2)
    Was only able to send 10 pounds because of the "great difficulty of procuring cash in this country"; mentions getting cash from "Uncle Tom" or tobacco from "Anderson" and converting that to cash; tobacco prices; discusses the loss Kentucky will feel at the death of Col. Christian.
  - Letter from J[ohn] Preston, n.p., to "brother," Francis Preston, [College of] William and Mary, [Williamsburg, Virginia]. 20 Nov. 1786., 3 pages. ALS. Including typescript of 1 page. (Folder 2)
    Discusses business dealings with Anderson tobacco, and obtaining the necessary materials and the carpenter recommended by Capt. T. Smith to finish their house; wants to compare prices between the Academy at Botetourt Town and William and Mary; gives details of building a new academy at Greenfield and the prices which would be charged.
  - Letter from J[ohn] Preston, "Smithfield," [Montgomery County, Virginia], to "brother," Francis Preston, Williamsburgh [sic], [Virginia], 26 Dec[embe]r 1786., 3 pages. ALS. Including typescript of 2 pages. (Folder 2)
    More discussion about the constructing of their house; expresses concern about a possible suit against them for a debt unpaid, unless they raise money from Anderson's tobacco; tells of neighbors anxiously awaiting his [FP] return so that they might "profit from your knowledge," [referring to Francis Preston's license to practice law] and so that he can be considered an eligible candidate; offers to campaign for him in his absence; relates feelings toward a duel fought between their cousin, James Breckenridge and [?] Younghusband.
  - Letter from J[ohn] Preston, "Smithfield," [Montgomery County, Virginia], to "brother," Francis Preston, Williamsburgh [sic], [Virginia], 17 Feb[ruar]y 1787., 3 pages. ALS. (Folder 2)
    Sends news of large amounts of mail for him, mainly on the subject of friendship; election day has been moved to an earlier date in April, requiring him [FP] to come home earlier; hopes this doesn't interfere with his studies; gives itinerary and details about coming home; discusses the other candidates and the main issue of the campaign--the division of the country; tells rumor that Congress is about to "raise a great army, for what purpose, we know not."
  - Bill of W[illia]m Galt & County 8-24 Dec[embe]r 1790., 2 pages. D. Including typescript of 2 pages. (Folder 2)
    Bill is for fabrics, clothes, and notions for "Sally B. Campbell" [later Sarah Buchanan (Campbell) Preston, wife of Francis Preston].
  - Letter from J[ohnl Preston, n.p. to "brother" Francis Preston, n.p., 5 May 1792., 2 pages. ALS. Including typescript of 1 page. (Folder 2)
    Short note discussing the election and political side effects relating to it.
  - Letter from J[ohn] Preston, Mr. McDowell's, to "Frank," Francis Preston, Montgomery [County, Virginia]. 29 Sept. 1792., 3 pages. ALS. Including typescript of 1 page. (Folder 2)
    Discusses land transactions and the upcoming change in the Judicial districts west of the Blue Ridge; mentions the end of the Indian War and the government being settled.
  - Letter from J[ohn] Preston, Jo[hn?] Breckenridge's, Lexington, [Virginia?], to Francis Preston, Washington County, Virginia, 31 May 1793., 3 pages. ALS. Including typescript of 2 pages. (Folder 2)
    Comments on the reformed behavior of B. Smith, a commander at one of the frontier posts, who has "abandoned both women and wine forever"; discussion of affairs with the Indians--treaties, not trusting them, and hopes of continuing the war with them; Gen[era]l Wayne, however, has orders only to defend themselves, not attack; mention of land prices connected with investment possibilities.
  - Letter from J[ohn] Preston, Lexington, [Virginia?] to "brother" Francis Preston, Abingdon, Washington County, [Virginia]. 8 Aug[us]t 1793., 3 pages. ALS. Including typescript of 2 pages. (Folder 2)
    Business discussion about an unknown matter.
  - Emancipation certificate, 20 Sept. 1793., 2 pages. DS. (Folder 2)
    Emancipation certificate of John Broady, Negro servant of William Campbell [father-in-law of Francis Preston]. Signed by Francis Preston.
  - Letter from J[ohn] Preston, Richmond, [Virginia] to "sister [In-law]," Sarah B. Preston, Philadelphia, [Pa.], 25 Nov[embe]r 1794., 3 pages. ALS. Including typescript of 1 page. (Folder 2)
    Mention of her domesticity; gossip of a rich widow, Mrs. Tho[ma]s Randolph, who has fallen in love with John Brown.
  - Letter from J[ohn] Preston, n.p., to "brother" [Francis Preston?], n.p., 25 Nov. 1794., Incomplete. 2 pages. ALS. Including typescript of 1 page. (Folder 2)
    Gives election news of senators and governor; details about a duel between Gen[era]1 Wood and W. Tho[ma]s Madison over the election of Governor [Brook] which led to defamations of character.
  - Letter from J[ohn] Preston, n.p., to Francis Preston, Congress, United States, [Philadelphia, Pennsylvania], 23 Jan[uar]y 1796., 1 page. ALS. (Folder 2)
    Concerning attention paid to brother William by Gen[era]l Wayne.
  - Letter from [Bishop] J[ames] Madison, Botetourt, [County, Virginia], to Francis Preston, Washington C[ount]y, [Virginia], 9 Sep[tember] 1797., 2 pages. ALS. (Folder 2)
    Discusses power of attorney between H. Smith and himself; and business matters dealing with land.
  - Letter from J[ohn] Preston, n.p., to "brother," Francis Preston, Washington [County, Virginia], 21 May 1798., 3 pages. ALS. Including typescript of 1 page. (Folder 2)
    Discusses business transactions, including buying some horses; shares feelings of wanting to be married.
  - Letter from J[ohn] Preston, "Smithfield," [Montgomery County, Virginia], to "brother" Francis Preston, Washington [County, Virginia], 27 Oct. 1798., 3 pages. ALS. Including typescript of 1 page. (Folder 2)
    Discussion of business transactions with Governor Shelby.
  - Letter from J[ohn] Preston, "Smithfield," [Montgomery County, Virginia], to "brother," Francis Preston, Washington [County, Virginia], 14 May 1799., 3 pages. ALS. Including typescript of 1 page. (Folder 2)
    Expresses concern over their brother "Tommy" not being able to attend school due to insufficient funds, and asks if he [FP] might be able to help in this area; mentions William and Mary as a good choice for Tommy to study law.
  - Letter from J[ohn] Preston, Horse Shoe [Bottom?], to "brother," Francis Preston, Washington [County, Virginia], 28 Oct. 1799., 2 pages. ALS. (Folder 2)
    Discussion about horses and his [John's] son cutting teeth.
  - Letter from J[ohn] Preston, Blacksburgh [sic], [Virginia], to "brother," Francis Preston, Washington [County, Virginia], 6 Nov. 1799., 2 pages. ALS. Including typescript of 1 page. (Folder 2)
    Family news; grandmother has died; is still looking for the book, Evans Millwright, sent by him [Francis] to use as reference for their spring water problem.
  - Letter from J[ohn] Preston, Horseshoe Bottom, to "brother," Francis Preston, Saltworks, Washington [County, Virginia], 6 Jan[uar]y 1802., 2 pages. ALS. Including typescript of 1 page. (Folder 3)
    Asks him to help with E. Madison's business affairs; house is half finished; hopes to pay off all debts soon and be as "independent as a freeman ought to be."
  - Letter from J[ohn] Preston, Horseshoe Bottom, to "brother," Francis Preston, Washington [County, Virginia], 27 Jan[uar]y 1802., 1 page. ALS. Including typescript of 1 page. (Folder 3)
    Wagon arrived satisfactorily; sent 5 bushels of hemp seed and will send more if needed; borrowed from him a bundle of "nail rods" to lay the plank floor in his home; talk of the birth of "another fine son " who is quite handsome.
  - Letter from J[ohn] Preston, Horseshoe Bottom, to "brother," Francis Preston, Saltworks, Washington [County, Virginia], 10 May 1802., 1 page. ALS. Including typescript of 1 page. (Folder 3)
    Business news; cotton and salt arrived; has sent nail rods in a different, lighter wagon.
  - Letter from J[ohn] Preston, "Smithfield," [Montgomery County, Virginia], to "brother" [Francis Preston], n.p., 19 Dec[embe]r 1802., 4 pages. ALS. Including typescript of 2 pages. (Folder 3)
    Political discussion-including the possibility of Congressional redistricting of Botetourt and Montgomery counties, the disagreements between the Federalists and the Republicans, and how redistricting would affect him [JP] when elections come again; ironworks are shorthanded and he is willing to hire out seven "of my best negroe men"; wife has had the mumps and self has had a bout with rheumatism.
  - Letter from David Campbell, Campbella, Tennessee, to Sarah B. Preston, Saltworks, Washington County, Virginia, 22 Ap[ri]l 1804., 3 pages. ALS. (Folder 3)
    Expresses joy at Mrs. Preston's recovering her health; philosophical statements concerning life; fondness toward Mrs. Preston and family; mention of who will be in school at Abingdon for the next two years, if the school stays open.
  - Letter from J[ohn] Preston, Horseshoe Bottom, to "brother," Francis Preston, Saltworks, Washington [County, Virginia], 22 D[ecembe]r [18]05., 1 page. ALS. Including typescript of 1 page. (Folder 3)
    Salt was delivered and all was in good order; family news including the birth of a son [William Ballard Preston] to their brother J[ames] P. Preston.
  - Letter from J[ohn] Preston, Horseshoe Bottom, to Francis Preston, Washington County, [Virginia], 2 March [18]07., 3 pages. ALS. Including typescript of 1 page. (Folder 3)
    Asks if he can send his son, Carlton Radford, to Mr. Whaley's school, since Mr. Birch's school at Fort Chizwell has broken up; has taken care of money matters; more problems with rheumatism.
  - Letter from J[ohn] Preston, Montgomery C[ourt] H[ouse] Virginia, to "brother;" Francis Preston, Saltworks, Washington County, [Virginia], 15 Feb[ruar]y 1808., 5 pages. ALS. Including typescript of 2 pages. (Folder 3)
    Asks for his son, William, to be sent home since the family is free of the whooping cough; a Senate position is open, but he [JP] declined since he thought that Francis wanted to run; discussion of war with Britain, and the election of a president; Virginia seems to be favoring Madison, but New York is doubtful; no plans yet for the Virginia militia to be called.
  - Letter from J[ohn] Preston, Richmond, [Virginia] to "brother," Francis Preston, Abingdon, Washington County, [Virginia], 30 Ap[ri]l [18]10., 3 pages. ALS. Including typescript of 1 page. (Folder 3)
    Business letter; alludes to wife's death; mother-in-law taking care of domestic business.
  - Letter from Jo[h]n Tyler, Gov[ernor of Virginia], "In Council Chamber," [Richmond, Virginia], to Co[lo]n[e]l Francis Preston, Abingdon Washington [County, Virginia], 4 May 1810., 1 page. ALS. (Folder 3)
    Cover letter for a commission for Sam[ue]l Preston, and a duplicate for the magistrates.
  - Letter from J[ohn] Preston, Richmond, [Virginia], to "brother," Francis Preston, Washington [County, Virginia], 25 May 1811., 3 pages. ALS. Including typescript of 2 pages. (Folder 3)
    Affectionate talk of family; money matters taken care of; carriage maker in Philadelphia has put the "Family Arms and Crests" on it, and has only the painting and the spring to take care of.
  - Letter from J[ohn] Preston, Richmond, [Virginia], to "brother," Francis Preston, Abingdon, Washington County, [Virginia], 8 May 1812., 3 pages. ALS. Including typescript of 1 page. (Folder 3)
    Happy that he won the election, even though it was with some difficulty; discussion of the ingratitude and jealousy of the community of those who "serve the public"; money and construction matters; legal concern over the exchange of properties, the Briar Patch and Horseshoe; wife is quite ill and still grieves over the death of Louisa.
  - Letter from Peter Randolph, Nottoway [County, Virginia], to Col. Francis Preston, Richmond, [Virginia], 10 Dec[embe]r 1812., 2 pages. ALS. (Folder 3)
    Concerning the addition of Mecklenburg into the 5th Circuit, Randolph's firm opposition to the plan requested by Judge Johnston to relieve Johnston of some duties of the 13th Circuit, and Randolph's reasons against the change of duties.
  - Letter from J[ohn] Preston, Richmond, [Virginia], to "brother," Francis Preston, Washington [County, Virginia], 3 Mar. 1813., 3 pages. ALS. Including typescript of 1 page. (Folder 3)
    Concern over the Blockading Squadron [of Great Britain], and description of naval battles in Lyn[n]haven Bay; wishes Congress would impose an embargo [on Great Britain].
  - Letter from Fran[ci]s Preston, Brig. Gen., 17th Brig., 3rd Div., n.p. to John Tate, n.p., 20 Dec. 1814., 1 page. ADS. (Folder 3)
    Appointment of Tate as Brigade Inspector of the 17th Brigade in the third division of the militia of the said Commonwealth. Including ADS on verso by Fran[ci]s Preston appointing Capt. Francis Smith as his aide, 16 May 1816.
  - Letter from J[ohn] Preston, Horseshoe Bottom, to "brother," Francis Preston, Abingdon, [Virginia], 9 Ap[ri]l 1815., 3 pages. ALS. (Folder 3)
    Is still trying to locate the papers of W. P. Preston; more election news; introduces S. P. Sharp.
  Series 3: John Preston Papers
- John Preston Papers, 1785-1819., 8 items. (Folder 4)
  - Letter from P[atrick] Henry, Richm[on]d, [Virginia], to John Preston, Montgomery [County, Virginia], 25 March 1785., 1 page. ALS. (Folder 4)
    Concerning a serjeanty right granted by Lord Dumore, 10 to 12 years prior, to him [Henry] for 200 acres on the Ohio [River].
  - Receipt of David Price for ₤ 3 received from John Preston, 17 April 1785., 1 page. DS. (Folder 4)
    Including ANS on verso by J[ohn] Preston, n.p., [17 April 1785], stating payment of ₤ 29 to William M. Miller. 1 p.
  - Letter from Ja[me]s Blair, Abingdon, [Virginia], to John Preston, "Smithfield," Montgomery [County, Virginia], 29 July 1790., 2 pages. ALS. (Folder 4)